Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and today we're
going to be going through the tips and
tricks for solving gas law problems.
And one thing that you might have
realized is that while learning all
these gas laws, there are a lot of
them and it's really difficult to
try to keep your brain straight.
When you are trying to solve
all these difficult problems.
So what we're going to go through
in this video is the tips and tricks
of how to essentially organize
your brain and how to do this.
The very first thing we are going
to be doing is while solving these
problems is we need to stay organized.
Therefore, you stay organized, you
get a good grade, which is exactly
what we want in a chemistry course.
So when we are staying organized,
what are we going to do?
Well, we need to write down what are given
and our desired terms are in the problem.
So when we look at a word problem,
we need to go word by word, sentence
by sentence, and try to highlight and
pick out all the key numbers and terms
that are being said in the problem and
look for little clues that are, that
are being hinted along the way of it.
Now, why is that important?
Well, one thing we're trying to do
is we need to be able to match those
given terms to To the formulas that
are being given, meaning you've
got to try to fit the puzzle pieces
together that we are being given.
Because one thing you might have
realized is that with gas laws and
specifically the chapters going
over that there are close to a dozen
formulas that you have come across.
And it can be quite overwhelming to
figure out which one is the right choice.
So we're going to go through that.
We're going to look at all
those guest laws from my
previous videos on guest laws.
So if you haven't covered those yet,
I would recommend going back to those
first before going through these ones,
because they are tougher examples.
All right.
So let's take a look at our guest
laws and let's go through some
different problems with them as well.
With the guest laws, there are two
major categories of guest laws.
So when you first started this, so in my
part one video, I talked about Boyle's
Law, Charles Law, and Gay Lussac's Law.
Afterwards, on part two, I talked about
Avogadro's and the Combined Gas Law.
Now, with all of these, right, there's a
lot of formulas that are involved here.
So how do you figure out which one to use?
Well, the big thing is, Is keeping
in mind that they are, we have to
be organized, write down our givens.
Now, what makes all these
formulas similar to one another?
What is the big thing?
So especially when we compare
these to the ideal gas law,
which is a little different.
So what makes these so different?
Well, the secret is in the subscripts.
So one thing is that you see here
is that there are a bunch of ones
and twos written on the screen.
Okay.
And that is telling you that
the system or the gases that
you're observing are changing.
So being that they are changing,
this is giving us a hint of
some sort of really big picture.
What is increasing?
What is decreasing?
How's the system compressing?
How's it expanding?
All these little key words that
we need to look at to be able
to see how is there change.
So if you see a different gas, balloon,
or system, or piston, or whatever term
changing, you're going to be using these.
And you're going to notice that because
you're going to have multiple pressure
values given, multiple volumes, multiple
temperatures, multiple moles, right?
So you're looking for all those changes.
So keep in mind for later.
Now, in comparison, the other set
of formulas, right, that wasn't
all of them, it's like all God.
There was the Ideal Gas Law,
and then there's Dalton's Law.
Now, for these two, one thing about them
is that they don't reference change.
These are referring to the
current condition of the gas.
Especially when you're looking at
something like the Ideal Gas Law, Notice
here that PV is equal to NRT, and there's
no subscripts by any of these values.
So what is that telling you?
It's asking you what is the
current state of your gas, and
that's the important thing.
Now with Dalton's Law,
you can be like, well, Dr.
Dan, you just said that there's no
subscripts here and there's a bunch here.
Well, this is referring to many
gases all shoved in the same balloon
or same environment that you're in.
Think of your room, for
example, that you're in.
You're breathing air.
What is air made out of?
Right?
It's oxygen.
What you need to breathe, but you're
in a nitrogen rich atmosphere.
So there's nitrogen, oxygen, CO2,
and all the other aromas and odors
that surround you at all times.
Those are all the gases.
But you can kind of see that
the total of each of these.
is referring to the current
situation that you're looking at.
So there's a difference.
You have current, and then you have how
it's going from one state to another.
What we're going to be doing is
we're going to be going through these
different, some harder problems to
try to identify and how I would think
about going through these problems.
Let's take a look.
All right.
The first problem is all
about being organized.
So, what is it?
Let's take a look.
Well, it says if 10 liter, a 10
liter balloon at STP has its pressure
increased, Two atmospheres and it's
temperatures increased 300 Kelvin.
Then what is the new volume?
Now looking at this problem,
that is a lot to unpack.
So let's take a look at what is here.
Well, the first term, what it tells you
as we go through the problem, it says
a 10 liter balloon leader is a volume.
So the first thing we want to
do is write down our volume,
which we have as 10 liters.
we Now, the next part that it
mentions is that, oh, it's an S T P.
Now, what was that?
S T P is a standardized
temperature and pressure.
So it's telling you it's at that
current condition and its condition
in this case is referring to what is
the standard temperature and pressure.
So the standard temperature is two
hundred and seventy three degrees.
Kelvin, and the pressure
is one atmosphere, so we're
going to write that down.
Now the next part says that it
has been increased, okay, there's
that key, one of those key words
that I was mentioning earlier.
The word increase, so we can see
that in a couple places in this
problem, what that's referring to
is that the conditions are changing.
So meaning we're going to be using
one of our earlier gas laws, right?
So one of the ones that we
have a condition change.
So what it tells you is that
the pressure was increased.
So okay, so we're going to have in
this problem, we're going to have
P2, which tells you, oh, this is
going to two atmospheres as a result.
So that's going to be changing.
Now it also mentions that the
temperature increased to 300
Kelvin, so that also increased.
And then ask you, okay, well,
what is your new volume?
So being organized, we're
writing down all of our values.
You need to write them down.
That's crucial.
So which formula will this match to?
So you're going to go through your list
and you're looking for, well, which
one of these uses three variables?
And one thing you're going to realize
is that your, uh, your, um, combined
gas law, the original version tells you,
okay, here we have all these variables.
So we're going to use it and plug
our variables in to solve it.
Now I know a lot of students are
not the most comfortable with
rearranging a math problem, but it
does make the math a lot easier.
If we do that, how exactly
can we rearrange it?
Well, first thing is, is we can try to,
we got to get volume by itself on the
right hand So the way we can do that is
essentially multiply the left, or sorry,
the right hand side and the left by the
inverse of pieces we don't need, which
are pressure and temperature on the right.
We'll do the same thing on the left, okay?
And then as a result, what's going to
happen is the pressure is going to cancel,
temperature is also going to cancel, so
what that's going to leave us with is
the only thing that we need essentially.
care about here is the volume.
All right.
So we'll have only the volume here.
We can kind of move this guy
around for ourselves, make it a
little bit easier to work with.
And we are now going to plug our,
our values into this new formula.
So, okay, let's do it.
So we have on the left, we have
300 Kelvin, and that's going to
be divided by two atmospheres.
Notice how we're trying to be organized,
plug in our different values, and that's
going to be multiplied by the original
left side, which is your pressure of
1 atmosphere times your volume, which
is 10 liters, and we're going to be
dividing all of that by 273 kelvins.
And you want to double check yourself that
you are putting down all of these values.
You want to make sure you don't
accidentally leave anything out just
because it is really easy to do so.
So once we put that on our calculator, we
can also kind of put all this together.
If it helps you see that, oh,
all this is one big fraction as
well, just like this, boop, boop.
We'll just multiply all
those little pieces.
So if we multiply the
top, it's 300 times 100.
1 times 10, and then we're going
to divide that by 2 times 273,
and when all that happens, what
we will get for volume 2 is 5.
49 liters is equal to the second volume.
Now does that make sense?
Well we can look at our values,
and if you remember, pressure
and temperature increase.
And pressure and volume, they
are opposites of each other.
So the pressure increases.
the volume should decrease as a result.
And that was a very substantial change.
It was doubled, and you can see
the volume is almost halved.
That's a result.
So this is doing the first one.
Let's take a look at another.
Well, the next important skill
for how to solve these gas law
or any math problem is how to
understand the concept of a constant.
So in these formulas, you can
see that you have pressures and
volumes and temperatures and moles.
They're on both sides of the equation.
Now when something is held
constant, meaning that it's not
changing, though, let's say it's
one atmosphere on the left and it's
still one atmosphere on the right.
Well, that value never changed.
So therefore it can be canceled out.
So let's show an example of
where that is, that is the case.
Now the good news is, is if
you remember, I showed you that
there were about six different
formulas, all involving subscripts.
Now, if you understand the concept
of constants, you can use the
combined gas law to solve almost
every single problem involving age.
In this problem, I'll show you how.
So if we have a glass jar at a constant
volume, so keep that in mind, right?
So let's kind of highlight
that for ourselves.
Constant volume with a leaky
lid, and it contains 0.
27 moles of air.
Okay.
Now, and this is going to be heated from
room temperature to a hundred degrees C.
So that con, uh, comment of
heating tells you, Oh, the
temperature is going to go up.
Now it also says that you have a constant
pressure, so pressure's not changing.
How many moles are left in your jar?
Okay.
So what formula are we going to
use here when this is happening?
Let's also kind of list out what we have.
So in this problem, we
have that N1 is equal to 0.
27 moles.
We want to know what N2 is, and
then we were given two temperatures.
So we had 22 degrees Celsius, and
then T2 was 100 degrees Celsius.
Now the thing is about gas
laws, you have to remember what
units can temperature be in.
It has to be in Kelvin.
So let's quick convert these to Kelvin.
So quick conversion is add 2 73
to each of your Celsius numbers.
So what we're going to get in terms
of Kelvin here, so we'll use a
different color, is we have, uh,
two 90, uh, 2 95 kelvin for T one,
and then T two is going to be 3 73.
So to do our quick conversion.
There is no quite formula that matches
this based on what we had before.
If you remember from earlier,
we had the following different
formulas, and none of them talk
about pressure and moles together.
Or sorry, not pressure and
moles, temperature and moles.
You see pressure and temperature,
volume and moles, volume and
temperature, none of them cover that.
So what can we use?
Well, the only thing that has both those
terms is this combined gas law that has
no specific assumptions to it, meaning
it's the expanded combined gas law.
It has moles in it.
It's an extra part.
So let's take a look
at how we can use that.
So we're going to be using
this expanded gas law to show
how we can take out constants.
So in the problem, it told you that
pressure and volume are constant,
meaning that they're not changing.
So there is no, essentially there's
no subscript for pressure and volume.
So we can actually kind of delete those.
And when we show this problem,
well, if they are the same.
They're going to cancel each other out.
So what we can actually do is
instead of putting pressure and
volume going to be the equivalent
of having a one on top because
they're this, they're the same value.
We don't know what the value
is, but you know that they're
the same because it's constant.
So now this formula here isn't
quite usable the way it is.
What we can do is to make it
usable is take the reciprocal
or the inverse, meaning flip the
fraction to put it in a usable form.
So what does that flip fraction look like?
Well, simply get rid of the one over TT
two and RT one and one and T two and two.
We have our new formula,
which is just this.
We got rid of everything else.
You can do this with any
problem involving change.
You can get rid of the constants.
From that, what do we want to solve for?
Well, we want N2 by itself, so
we'll divide both sides by T2,
effectively moving it over, and
therefore getting our new formula.
So let's plug in our values.
So T1 is 295 Kelvin and we are
going to be multiplying that by 0.
27 moles.
And then we're going to
divide that by 373 Kelvin.
So now when that happens, what
you're going to get is 295 times 0.
27, divide that number
by 373 and we will get 0.
21 moles.
of air is left in your jar.
So we can make a new formula.
And one thing to keep in mind too,
is if you remember that relationship
here, being there in an inverse
relationship, as temperature
increases, moles should go down.
And it did, which is great to see.
Let's take a look at some different
skills to master in this video.
The next skill that's going to be
very useful is how to find molar mass.
Now, why is this something
that's so important?
Well, it helps you to be able to
identify what gas you have in that
you can't usually see the gases.
So you can measure what they're all
about, but you might not be able to just
identify by looking around you being
like, Oh, what gas is all around my head.
You have to be able to do
calculations to solve that.
So in this problem, I have 2.
787 grams sample of gas, and it's
found to occupy a volume of 2.
45 liters.
At 300 Kelvin and 1 atmosphere.
We know that it's an elemental diatomic.
Which one is it?
Let's try to find out.
So the first thing to think of is,
well, when it comes to molar mass,
which allows you to identify different
substances, it's like the fingerprint
for a lot of these molecules.
It's one way to do that.
So if I am to think of molar mass, right?
Like that was grams over.
Moles, well in this problem
I have my grams, right?
So the way that we could
essentially solve this is I know 2.
787 moles.
grams on top, but I don't
know my moles, which is N.
So which formula can solve for moles?
Well, this is where we'll
use the ideal gas law.
PV is equal to nRT.
So being that is one thing you
will notice is that this particular
gas is at its current condition.
Notice how there's no change involved.
There's one volume, one
pressure, one temperature.
There's nothing else.
So what we are going to end up
doing is we are going to plug
those values and solve for N.
So we are going to rearrange the ideal gas
law to get N by itself, and it's going to
be pressure times volume divided by R T.
So now what is R in case you're wondering?
That's just a constant value.
And we're going to use it that we got
to always make sure the units match
what we are being given in the problem.
So if they don't match, you're
going to get, you're going to
be really sad because you're not
going to get the correct answer.
So our pressure is one atmosphere,
so that's going to go on top.
We have our volume, which is 2.
45 liters, and that's going to
be divided by R, which is 0.
08206.
And that has a very complex set of
units, liter, atmosphere, mole, kelvin.
And then that's going to be times
temperature, which is 300 kelvin.
Okay, now when we're putting this in
our calculators, you need to make sure
that you are either using the fraction
button to separate top and bottom or use
parentheses to separate them as well.
So when we solve this, what we are
going to get for the number of moles
in the problem is a number around 0.
0995 and then a bunch of
decimals after that, and that's
going to be units of moles.
Now, does that match any molar mass?
Well, we're not quite done, right?
This number here has to, you
have to plug it in to the value,
to the term that we had above.
So if we take this value from
before, so we are going to
plug in our new number for n.
So let's take that and this
will be grams over moles.
And what, by putting these two
things in your calculator, you're
essentially Simplifying it.
So we do 2.
787 divide by 0995, hit enter,
and what you are going to get is a
value close to 28 grams per mole.
Now which diatomic gas is this?
Is it?
Well, that's one thing you have to be
able to remember, is your diatomics.
And if you're not sure about them,
watch my video on the seven diatomic
gases, because it's very important.
So let's take a look at
the list of diatomics.
Alright, if you remember my saying,
have no fear of ice cold beer, you
will never forget the seven diatomics.
So diatomic means two.
So being that we had a molar mass of 28
grams per mole, we're So if you divide
that number by 2, you will get 14.
So which element matches 14?
Well, it's not hydrogen.
Oh, nitrogen is 14.
So 14 times 2 is 28.
So our diatomic in this case is N2 gas.
And that will be our
answer for this problem.
So sometimes you got to try to
solve the mystery of what gas
can be located in our sample.
So we did it this time.
Let's see if we can do
it again in the future.
All right, let's go on
to the next problem.
Okay.
Sometimes you will be given problems
that involve diagrams and you have
to be able to read what they're
showing, especially when they show
them in different atoms and molecules.
And a lot of times they're
referring to mixtures.
So in this case, we have a mixture and
it's sealed in this container that I have.
Let's use a diagram to answer
the following questions.
So the first thing is you can see
that in this purple vial here,
I have four different gases.
And the first thing I ask
you is, okay, which gas has
the highest partial pressure?
Well, how can we do that?
Well, this is where Dalton's
law comes into play.
Dalton's law had two different formulas
that were really important, right?
If you add up every pressure of each
gas, you will get the total pressure.
Same thing about moles.
If you add the moles of each
individual gas, being that they're
indistinguishable particles from one
another, you can't just count all the
little air molecules around you and
figure out what's nitrogen, oxygen.
You just know what the
pressure of your room is.
You don't know what's each,
but we can try to calculate it.
We can approximate.
So based on that, what that means is,
well, whichever molecule has the most
moles is exuding your highest pressure.
So what we need to simply do
in these types of problems
is count what we have, right?
As if you could count.
So if we count the number of oxygens
here, we're going to count each
individual one of these little orbs here.
So you see a one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven red oxygens.
So we are going to put a.
For nitrogen or ammonia, we have
one, two, three, four, five.
We will put a five here for HCL gas.
We have one, two, three,
four, five as well.
And then neon, which is our purple,
we have one, two, three, four in our
molecule here in our different, uh,
our number of Forbes that we have.
All right.
So which one is the highest?
Well, being that oxygen has the
most, this is, this is having the
most pressure out of all of them.
So oxygen will be the most, the least
amount of pressure would be neon because
it has the lowest number of moles.
So O2 is our answer.
Now let's go on to another one.
So if we assume each gas particle is
one mole, what is the mole fraction NH3?
Well, okay, so mole fraction,
what is that referring to?
Well, if you look at this formula here,
where partial pressure is equal to the
total pressure times n one, n I over n
total, what this part is in parentheses
here, this is your mole fraction.
Okay.
So mole fraction.
And usually the way that this guy is,
is labeled is with the Greek letter I to
represent that you have a mole fraction.
So if you ever see that, like that fancy
looking X, that's telling you, Hey,
this is talking about the mole fraction.
So the way it is, is if you remember
before I counted everything for us.
So if we add up all those,
remember each one is equal to one.
So we can get our total really easily.
So we do 7 plus 5, that's 12.
12 plus 5 is 17.
17 plus 4 is 21.
So what we will put as our total, so
we'll put that on the bottom, so we got
21 moles total of gas, and that's adding
all the and it's asking us what's the,
what's the mole fraction of ammonia.
So ammonia we had five from
earlier, so we are going to put
that we had five moles of ammonia.
So this is the literal
definition of a mole fraction,
so five over 21 in this case.
Now depending on who your teacher
is and how the homeworks are, you
either have to put it as a fraction,
so five over 21, or you can put that
in your calculator and simplify it.
So if we did five divided
by 21, we will get 0.
238.
With that value, you will notice
that there is no units between it
being that moles technically cancels
here because it's just a fraction.
It's just a ratio of what
we're trying to represent.
Now the last part is assume each gas
represents one mole like we did before.
The total pressure of the container is 1.
20 atmospheres.
What is the partial
pressure, pressure of HCL?
So earlier I had that five mole, there
was five moles of HCL just to remind
us of how many we had in our container.
So how can we do this?
So let's use this partial pressure
equation that we've been, I've
been kind of dancing around.
So in this case, we want to know
what the partial pressure of HCL
is so that we'll replace our I.
Because I is just an indice,
it's just however you label it.
In this case, we are labeling it as HCl.
So we have our total pressure, which is 1.
20 atmospheres, and then we're going
to times that by our mole fraction.
So that was 5 moles all over 21,
which was the total number of moles.
So that was all the little molecules
that were in the container.
So when we do 1.
2 times 5 divided by 21, what
we are going to get is 0.
286 atmospheres of HCl.
And atm is atmospheres, not at
the moment, it is atmospheres,
just so everybody knows.
All right, so that is our
value here for this problem.
Okay, so that wraps up our video on
tips and tricks for solving gas laws.
Which as you could see, gas laws can
get very, very complicated and complex.
So please refer to my other videos
on how to practice these, which go
through many examples through all the
different gas laws and how to use them.
And as I was saying earlier, the
biggest thing take home messages
is you need to stay organized.
Write down what your, all your values are.
So that way you can match them to your
different gas law formulas, which is
always the most important part is that
being that we do have all these gas laws.
Is you need to be able to read the word
problem carefully and look for if there
is change or if it's the current state.
That is what's most important.
If you can notice that, the more you
practice, the easier it will get.
You can do this.
I know you're capable of doing this.
You're smart.
You're intelligent.
You can do it.
So keep, keep practicing.
Let me know if you need any
help in the comments or in
class or in discord or wherever.
And let me know everything
I can do to help you.
And if you're someone just
watching this for help, please hit
that like and subscribe button.
And if you see me on campus, say hi.
All right.
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.